<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<dataset xmlns="https://gitlab.mpcdf.mpg.de/dcfidalgo/llamore"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="https://gitlab.mpcdf.mpg.de/dcfidalgo/llamore
    ../../schema/xsd/dataset.xsd"
    source="https://doi.org/10.3249/1868-1581-2-2-Clark">
    <title>Legal-Historical article with footnotes/marginal notes ()</title>
    <description content-type="text/html"><![CDATA[ 
    <p>Source: Roger S. Clark: "Amendments to the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court Considered at the first Review Conference on the Court, Kampala, 31 May-11 June 2010", in: Goettingen Journal of International Law 2/2 (2010), pp. 689-711, https://doi.org/10.3249/1868-1581-2-2-Clark</p>
  ]]></description>
    <instance xml:id="instance-1">
        <description content-type="text/html"><![CDATA[ 
      <h2>Footnote</h2>
    ]]></description>
        <input type="raw"><![CDATA[1 Ludwig Wittgenstein, Tractatus logico-philosophicus, London 1922, 1.1.]]></input>
        <output type="segmented-instance">
            <note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
                n="1"
                type="footnote"
                place="bottom">
                <label>1</label>
                <bibl>Ludwig Wittgenstein, Tractatus logico-philosophicus, London 1922, 1.1</bibl>.
            </note>
        </output>
    </instance>
</dataset>

<!-- 
1 U.N. Doc.A/CONF.183/9, 17 July 1998.
2 The stocktaking entailed a rich review of the topics of complementarity, cooperation, the impact of the Rome Statute system on victims and affected communities, and peace and justice. There are some very useful papers on these issues on the Court’s website for the Conference. For the conference website http://www.icc-cpi.int/Menus/ASP/ReviewConference/ (last visited 20 August 2010). Perhaps the most distressing fact to emerge from the discussions is that fewer than half of the parties to the Statute have adopted adequate domestic implementation legislation to give effect to the treaty.
3 The Assembly had the power to set the agenda for the Conference. Meeting the previous November, it took a cautious view of the amendments that could be considered, limiting the agenda to the three just noted. One of the three, possible deletion of Art. 124, was required to be on the agenda by the article’s own terms; aggression had been the subject of extensive preparatory work since 1998 and it was inconceivable that it would not be considered, even if it was not strictly required to be so; there was wide agreement on the weapons provision by late 2009, but a number of other potential additions to Art. 8 did not proceed to Kampala in the absence of a fairly clear consensus on them. See infra at notes 71-77. So too, proposals relating to addition of crimes of terrorism and serious drug crimes to the subject-matter of the Statute were left over to future meetings of the Assembly of States Parties, and indeed, potentially, to later Review Conferences. See infra at notes 78-80. (Art. 123 empowers the ASP to call future Review Conferences, but does not indicate any particular time frame. There seems to be a widespread disposition to have reviews on a regular basis, perhaps on a seven-year cycle.).
4 Rome Statute, supra note 1, Art. 120: “No reservations may be made to this Statute.”.
5 Apparently the permanent Five members of the Security Council had agreed a day or two earlier that their bottom line was that there should be a ten-year opt-out period in respect of both war crimes (Art. 8) and crimes against humanity (Art. 7), but the United Kingdom and France opted out of that agreement.
6 See Resolution ICC-ASP/8/Res. 6, 26. November 2009, Annex I.
7 Art. 124 ICC Statute, RC/Res.4 (2010).
8 The Crime of Aggression, RC/Res. 6 (2010).
9 Rome Statute, supra note 1, Art. 5 (1).
10 Id., Art. 5 (2).
11 Final Act of the United Nations Diplomatic Conference of Plenipotentiaries on the Establishment of an International Criminal Court, Annex I, Resolution F, para. 7, U.N. Doc. A/CONF.183/10, 17 July 1998, at 8-9 [Resolution F].
12 The last draft on the table at the Preparatory Commission was a Discussion Paper proposed by the Coordinator on the Crime of Aggression, U.N. Doc. PCNICC/2002/2/Add.2 [Discussion Paper], discussed in R. S. Clark, ‘Rethinking Aggression as Crime and Formulating its Elements: The Final Work-Product of the Preparatory Commission for the International Criminal Court’, 15 Leiden Law Journal (2002) 4, 859.
13 Report of the Special Working Group on the Crime of Aggression, Doc. ICC-ASP/7/SWGCA/2 (2009) [2009 Report]. The proposed amendments and the proposed “Elements” (see next note) are also contained in Annex II to Resolution ICC-ASP/8/Res. 6, supra note 6. Concerning the provisions on aggression in general, see N. Weisbord, ‘Prosecuting Aggression’, 49 Harvard International Law Journal (2008) 1, 161; S. Barriga, ‘Against the Odds: The Results of the Special Working Group on the Crime of Aggression’, in G. R. Bellilli ed., International Criminal Justice (2010); ‘Symposium: The Codification of the Crime of Aggression’, 20 European Journal of International Law (2009) 4, 1103. Not all the contributors to the European Journal symposium are true believers. Another who is skeptical of the whole exercise is G. Simpson, ‘“Stop Calling it Aggression”: War as Crime’, 61 Current Legal Problems (2008), 191. The bulk of the Special Working Group’s substantive work was done at intercessional meetings held at the Liechtenstein Institute on Self-Determination at Princeton University. The SWGCA’s materials are usefully collected in S. Barriga, W. Danspeckgruber & C. Wenaweser (eds.), The Princeton Process on the Crime of Aggression: Materials of the Special Working Group on the Crime of Aggression, 2003-2009 (2009).
14 Informal intercessional meeting on the Crime of Aggression, hosted by the Liechtenstein Institute on Self-Determination, Woodrow Wilson School, at the Princeton Club, New York, from 8 to 10 June 2009, Doc. ICC-ASP/8/INF.2 (2009), Appendix I [Draft Elements of Crimes]. There is a useful explanatory note on the elements in Annex II of the Report (“Non-paper by the Chairman on the Elements of Crimes”). Art. 9 of the Rome Statute required the production of Elements for genocide, crimes against humanity and war crimes. Resolution F required them for aggression; the SWGCA recommended an amendment to Art. 9 to make clear that aggression, too, requires its Elements. Elements emphasize, in more detail than the Statute, what the prosecution must prove in order to show that there was a crime; they also make some of the connections between the definitions in the “special part” of the Statute (Arts 6, 7 and 8, and now 8bis) and the “general principles” contained in Part III of the Statute. See generally, discussion of Art. 9 of the Statute (“Elements of Crimes”) in O. Triffterer (ed.), Commentary on the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court – Observers’ Notes, Article by Article, 2nd ed. (2008), 505.
15 Res. 6, supra note 8, annex II.
16 ‘International Military Tribunal (Nuremberg), Judgment and Sentences’, 41 American Journal of International Law (1947) 1, 172, 221.
17 Article 8bis (2), supra note 8, Annex I.
18 Id. The list of acts that “qualify as an act of aggression” is: invasion, annexation, bombardment, blockade, attack on the armed forces of another State, using forces that are in a State by consent in contravention of the terms of their presence, allowing a State’s territory to be used for the purposes of aggression by another, and sending by or on behalf of a State of armed bands, groups, irregulars or mercenaries, which carry out acts of armed force against another State.
19 G.A. Res. 3314 (XXIX), 14. December 1974, 29 U.N. GAOR, 29 th Sess., Supp. No. 31, U.N. Doc. A/9631, at 142.
20 Rome Statute, supra note 1, Art. 22 – “Nullum crimen sine lege”.
21 Art. 8bis (1), supra note 8, Annex I.
22 As well as the leadership language contained in Art. 8bis (5) of the amendments adopted in Kampala (in an apparent abundance of caution) adds a para. 3bis to Art. 25 (3) of the Statute which deals with individual responsibility: In respect of the crime of aggression, the provisions of this article shall apply only to persons in a position effectively to exercise control over or to direct the political or military action of a State.
23 See K. J. Heller, ‘Retreat from Nuremberg: The Leadership Requirement in the Crime of Aggression’, 18 European Journal of International Law (2007) 3, 477.
24 See Informal intercessional meeting of the Special Working Group on the Crime of Aggression, held at the Liechtenstein Institute on Self-Determination, Woodrow Wilson School, Princeton University, from 11 to 14 June 2007, Doc. ICC-ASP/6/SWGCA/INF.1 (2007) at 3, para. 12. This preparatory work seems to support the proposition that industrialists are potentially covered by the amendments, although no formal language to that effect was added.
25 Supra note 21. The Introduction to the Draft Elements of Crimes for aggression, supra note 14, stated that: “The term ‘manifest’ is an objective qualification.” There is a comment in the Report of the 2009 Intercessional meeting on the crime of aggression, supra note 14, at 6, para. 25, that “the Court would apply the standard of the ‘reasonable leader’, similar to the standard of the ‘reasonable soldier’ which was embedded in the concept of manifestly unlawful orders in article 33 of the Rome Statute.” The phrase “character, gravity and scale” provides a framework for forging such an objective standard. The best analysis of this threshold is J. Potter, The Threshold in the Proposed Definition of the Crime of Aggression, 6 N.Z. Y.B. I NT’ L L. (2008), 155. See also understanding adopted in Kampala, infra note 32.
26 See e.g., 2009 SWGCA Report, supra note 13 at 3, para. 13: “It was argued that the clause was unnecessary because any act of aggression would constitute a manifest violation of the Charter … and that the definition should not exclude any acts of aggression. … Other delegations expressed support for the threshold clause which would provide important guidance for the Court, and in particular prevent the Court from addressing borderline cases.” Some speakers thought it might help in analyzing a (rare) case of principled humanitarian intervention or a case more generally where the legality of the action was definitely in doubt.
27 The Nuremberg Charter had a puzzling requirement of a “war of aggression” which prompted the International Military Tribunal to draw a de facto distinction between the conquests of Austria and Czechoslovakia (achieved without actual fighting) on the one hand, and the invasions of Poland and others (achieved with considerable fighting) on the other. The former were classified as “acts of aggression” (and not yet “criminal”), the latter as “wars of aggression” and proscribed under the Charter. Control Council Law No. 10, under which subsequent prosecutions were brought, had language broad enough to treat Austria and Czechoslovakia as criminal aggressions. See generally, R. S. Clark, ‘Nuremberg and the Crime against Peace’, 6 Washington University Global Studies Law Review (2007) 3, 527.
28 Supra note 19. Cf. 2002 Discussion Paper, supra note 12 (containing alternative which would modify the Res. 3314 list by requiring that the act of aggression be one that “amounts to a war or aggression or constitutes an act which has the object or the result of establishing a military occupation of, or annexing, the territory of another State or part thereof”).
29 Art. 8bis, following the drafting style of the other substantive articles in the Statute, does not address specifically grounds of justification or excuse. Such matters, called “grounds for the exclusion of responsibility”, fall to be analyzed by the Court under the general part of the Statute, and, in particular, under article 31 thereof. The requirement that a breach be “manifest” provides an alternative route to analyze some of the “defences”. Obviously, that state is acting in self-defence as understood under the UN Charter, or as authorized by the Security Council, means that there is no act of aggression, without getting to the “manifest” issue. Other cases may be more difficult.
30 Statement by Harold Koh to the Conference, 4 June 2010, available at http://www.state.gov/s/l/releases/remarks/142665.htm (last visited 19 August 2010).
31 Supra note 8, annex III.
32 Paragraph 7 here underscores the “and” in the phrase “character, gravity and scale”.
33 Rome Statute, supra note 1, Art. 5 (2), second sentence.
34 G.A. Res. 377(V) A, 3. November 1950. The relevant provision reads: [The General Assembly] “Resolves that if the Security Council, because of lack of unanimity of the permanent members, fails to exercise its primary responsibility for the maintenance of international peace and security in any case where there appears to be a threat to the peace, breach of the peace, or act of aggression, the General Assembly shall consider the matter immediately with a view to making appropriate recommendations to Members for collective measures, including in the case of a breach of the peace or act of aggression the use of armed force when necessary, to maintain or restore international peace and security.”.
35 Most recently in Armed Activities on the Territory of the Congo (DR Congo v. Uganda), Jurisdiction of the Court, Judgment, ICJ Reports 2005.
36 See the 2002 Coordinator’s Paper, supra note 12. This was the effect of the words “which has been determined to have been committed by the State concerned” which appeared then in paragraph 2 of the definition. The whole context made it clear that someone other than the Court would make the determination.
37 Rome Statute, supra note 1, Art. 30, has a general rule that the crimes in the Statute must be accompanied by “intent and knowledge”.
38 In the structure of the Statute, a mistake is the obverse of knowledge or intent – it negatives a mental element of a crime. Rome Statute Art. 32 says that a mistake of fact shall be a ground for excluding criminal responsibility only if it negates the mental element required by the crime. It continues that a mistake of law as to whether a particular type of conduct is a crime within the jurisdiction of the Court shall not be a ground for excluding criminal responsibility. Finally, it adds that a mistake of law may, however, be a ground for excluding criminal responsibility if it negates the mental element required by such a crime, or in certain cases of superior orders. A defense that “I made a mistake about the legality of the conduct later held to be aggression” might be potentially open to one charged with the crime of aggression. The Elements of the crime of aggression work a finesse that is commonly applied to Elements of the war crimes under Art. 8 of the Statute by re-directing the enquiry in the direction of the facts. The relevant Element is thus: “The perpetrator was aware of the factual circumstances that established that such a use of armed force was inconsistent with the Charter of the United Nations.”
39 Supra notes 25-32.
40 Draft Art. 15bis (5) of the 2009 Report, supra note 13, provided: “A determination of an act of aggression by an organ outside the Court shall be without prejudice to the Court’s own findings under this Statute.”.
41 Id. Draft Art. 15bis, paras 2-4.
42 Id. Draft Art. 15bis,, para. 4, Alternative 2, Option 1.
43 Art. 15ter, supra note 8, para. 1, Article 13 (b) of the Rome Statute, supra note 1, permits Security Council referrals to the Court.
44 Art. 15ter, supra note 8, para. 2.
45 Id., para. 3.
46 Rome Statute, supra note 1, Art. 121 (3).
47 And see Understandings, supra note 8, annex III, para. 1. It is understood that the Court may exercise jurisdiction on the basis of a Security Council referral in accordance with Art. 13 (b) of the Statute only with respect to crimes of aggression committed after a decision in accordance with Art. 15ter (3) is taken, and one year after the ratification or acceptance of the amendments by thirty States Parties, whichever is later. Note also Resolution 6 itself, supra note 8, in para. 4 of which the Review Conference decided “to review the amendments on the crime of aggression seven years after the beginning of the Court’s exercise of jurisdiction.”.
48 The Conference presumably found power to impose conditions such as these under the general reference in Art. 5 (2) ICC Statute to “setting out the conditions” for the exercise of jurisdiction over aggression.
49 This is the general rule on Security Council referrals (as exercised in the case of Sudan and Darfur, Sudan not being a party to the Statute). The “preconditions” for a Security Council referral in Art. 12 of the ICC Statute do not include the requirement, as in the case of state and proprio motu referrals, that either the state of territoriality or the state of nationality be party to the Statute. See also Understandings, supra note 8, annex III, para. 2: It is understood that the Court shall exercise jurisdiction over the crime of aggression on the basis of a Security Council referral in accordance with Art. 13 (b) of the Statute, irrespective of whether the State concerned has accepted the Court’s jurisdiction in this regard.
50 Supra note 13 and 40, derived from the SWGCA draft. Note, however, that a referral by the Security Council does not necessarily entail a determination that an act of aggression has occurred, although it may. The Council may simply conclude that there is a prima facie case, but leave the rest to the Court.
51 See references in fn. 36, 37.
52 Res. 6, supra note 8, Art.15bis para. 1.
53 Id., para. 2.
54 Id., para. 3.
55 Id., para. 4. Prior to Kampala, there had been some discussion of the appropriate modalities for adoption and ratification or acceptance of the provisions making the jurisdiction over aggression effective. This took the form of attempts to interpret Art. 121 (3), (4) and (5) of the Rome Statute, the article on amendment. The correct analysis of language that became confusing in the last few days of the Rome Conference could perhaps never be ascertained with certainty. I interpret Art. 15bis (4) as a finesse of that whole issue, done by consensus of the Parties. Objecting Parties have their opt-out rights, something not entirely satisfactory to all, but the trade-off is that the provisions can become operative in a reasonable time and with intelligible procedural hurdles. There is, perhaps, a (less-than-convincing) counter-argument in para. 1 of Resolution 6, supra note 8, in which the Review Conference: “1. Decides to adopt, in accordance with Article 5, paragraph 2, of the Rome Statute of the International Criminal Court (hereinafter: “the Statute”) the amendments to the Statute contained in annex I of the present resolution, which are subject to ratification or acceptance and shall enter into force in accordance with Art. 121, paragraph 5; and notes that any State Party may lodge a declaration referred to in Art.15 bis prior to ratification or acceptance.” I think this must just be referring to the time frame for the ratification to become effective, thus setting up the requirement of entry into force a year after the 30 are obtained. If all State Parties are not to be bound, the opt-out option makes no sense. Compare the resolution on weapons, infra note 70, which makes clear the application of the amendments only to those who specifically accept them. Notice that an opt-out declaration may be made at any time, even before the necessary passage of seven years or the receipt of thirty ratifications.
56 Res. 6, supra note 8, Art. 15bis (5). The argument is that, whatever one might think about jurisdiction over genocide and the other crimes so far as non-parties acting on the territory of parties, aggression is of a different political and juridical dimension and should be treated differently.
57 See also the related point made in Understanding 5, supra note 8, annex III, that “the amendments shall not be interpreted as creating the right or obligation to exercise domestic jurisdiction with respect to an act of aggression committed by another State.” Customary law on universal jurisdiction over aggression (and perhaps even victim state jurisdiction) may not be as developed as it is in relation to other international crimes, and this language is at least neutral, and perhaps discouraging, of developments in custom in this area. Is aggression different?
58 Res. 6, supra note 8, Art. 15bis (6).
59 Id,. Art. 15bis (7).
60 Id., Art 15bis (8). This is followed by the statement also found in 15ter (4), supra note 13 and 50, that “[a] determination of an act of aggression by an organ outside the Court shall be without prejudice to the Court’s own findings under this Statute”.
61 See J.-M. Henckaerts, & L. Doswald-Beck, for International Committee of the Red Cross, Customary International Humanitarian Law Volume I: Rules, 243 (examples of weapons causing unnecessary suffering, beginning with barbed lances and barbed spears), 249 (examples of indiscriminate weapons).
62 See J. G. Stewart, ‘Towards a single definition of armed conflict in international humanitarian law: A critique of internationalized armed conflict,’ 85 International Review of the Red Cross (2003) 313; L. Moir, ‘Grave Breaches and Internal Armed Conflicts’, 7 Journal of International Criminal Justice (2009) 4, 763.
63 Rome Statute, supra note 1, Art. 8 (2) (b).
64 This and other proposals for amendment that got as far as the November meeting of the Assembly of States Parties are contained in Report of the Bureau on the Review Conference, Doc. ICC-ASP/8/43/Add.1, dated 10 November 2009 and in Report of the Working Group on the Review Conference, Annex II to Vol. I, Official Records of the Eighth Session of the Assembly of States Parties. Doc. ICC-ASP/8/20 (2009). At the November meeting, the International Committee of the Red Cross commented in a statement that “[t]he prohibitions of poison or poisoned weapons, asphyxiating, poisonous or other gases as well as bullets which expand or flatten easily in the body, are well-established under customary international law applicable in all armed conflicts and are an expression of the prohibition of weapons that are of a nature to cause superfluous injury or unnecessary suffering or are by nature indiscriminate. Conduct in violation of these prohibitions should therefore be criminalized in all armed conflicts.” (Statement by ICRC to Assembly of States Parties, on file with author.).
65 Amendments to Art. 8 of the Rome Statute, RC/Res. 5 (2010).
66 They also have an arguably legitimate role in domestic police work, where there is a danger to such persons as hostages, dignitaries, other police officers or bystanders if bullets aimed at criminals go through them and hit someone else.
67 Representatives of several armed forces assured the author in Kampala that their troops are armed with a very limited supply of such bullets, carefully kept aside for such events and used sparingly. Belgium, it appears, manufactures such ammunition.
68 The relevant Element of the war crime of employing prohibited bullets adopted in Kampala for non-international armed conflict mirrors precisely that for international armed conflict: “The perpetrator was aware that the nature of the bullets was such that their employment would uselessly aggravate suffering or the wounding effect.”.
69 Weapons adopting resolution, supra note 65, preambular paragraph 9, 2.
70 In accordance with Art. 121 (5) of the Rome Statute, supra note 1, this amendment to Art. 8 will apply only to those States Parties to the Statute who specifically ratify or accept it. This is specifically acknowledged in preambular paragraph 2, 1 of the resolution adopting the weapons amendment, supra note 65. Compare the finesse of the issue in the aggression amendment, supra note 55.
71 Such weapons are banned by the Convention on the Development, Production, Stockpiling and Use of Chemical Weapons and on Their Destruction, 3 September 1992, 1974 U.N.T.S. 45. Most chemical weapons appear to be banned in warfare under the Geneva Protocol for the Prohibition of the Use in War of Asphyxiating, Poisonous or Other Gases, and of Bacteriological Methods of Warfare, 17 June 1925, 94 L.N.T.S. 65 [Geneva Protocol], which is reiterated in Art. 8 (2) (b) (xviii) of the Rome Statute, but this is not free from doubt; thus there should probably be express references in the Rome Statute to the later treaty. Drafts on the table in Rome until a very late stage included chemical weapons but the reference to such weapons was deleted in the last few days of the conference.
72 Biological weapons are prohibited under the 1925 Geneva Protocol, supra note 71, along with asphyxiating and poisonous gases. There are further regime-articulating provisions dealing with them in the Convention on the Prohibition of the Development, production and Stockpiling of Bacteriological (Biological) and Toxin Weapons and Their Destruction, 10. April 1972, 1015 U.N.T.S. 163. Biological weapons were deleted from the draft of the Statute along with chemical weapons; there is no reference to them at all in the final Statute.
73 Anti-personnel mines are prohibited under the Convention on the Prohibition of the Use, Stockpiling, Production and Transfer of Anti-personnel Mines and on Their Destruction, 18 September 1997, 2056 U.N.T.S. 211 [the “Ottawa Convention”]. At the time of Rome, the ink was barely dry on this Convention and it had not yet come into force. It is now widely ratified, having 156 parties by mind-2010. There are still some major powers, like the United States, that have not come aboard.
74 Such weapons are prohibited in Protocol I (Non-Detectable Fragments) to the 1980 Convention on Prohibitions or Restrictions on the Use of Certain Conventional Weapons which may be deemed to be Excessively Injurious or to have Indiscriminate Effects, 10 October 1980, 1342 U.N.T.S. 137.
75 Protocol IV to the 1980 Convention, supra note 74, on Blinding Laser Weapons, 13 October 1995, 2024 U.N.T.S. 163, 167 (Doc. No. CCW/CONF.I/16 Part I).
76 See Diplomatic Conference for the Adoption of a Convention on Cluster Munitions, Dublin, May 19-30, 2008, Convention on Cluster Munitions, Doc. No. CCM/77 (30 May 2008), available at http://www.clusterconvention.org/downloadablefiles/ccm77_english.pdf (last visited 17 August 2010). Arguably, this Convention is not ripe enough for inclusion in the Rome Statute since it is not yet overwhelmingly adopted. It came into force on 1 August 2010, six months after receipt of 30 ratifications.
77 See Doc. ICC-ASP/8/43/Add. 1, supra note 64 (Annex III), at 9; Doc. ICC-ASP/8/20, Vol. I, supra note 64 (Annex II, Appendix II), at 64.
78 Id., 8/43/Add. 1 (Annex IV), at 12; 8/20, Vol. I (Appendix III) at 65.
79 Id., 8/43/Add. 1 (Annex VI) at 16; 8/20, Vol. I (Appendix IV) at 67.
80 The additional argument that terrorism should not be included in the Statute because it is not yet defined is something of a red herring. There is a widely agreed list of suppression treaties that deal with many of the cases of terrorism. It would be easy enough to include such a list as an interim “definition” to be supplemented should the General Assembly ever complete its work on a “general” terrorism convention. Which are the most serious drug crimes and thus appropriate for international jurisdiction is a fair question. The Trinidad and Tobago/Belize draft approached this in a creative manner that certainly provides a basis for further discussion. Their draft in the Report of the Bureau on the Review Conference, supra note 64, (at 16) would authorize ICC jurisdiction over assorted breaches of the 1961 Single Convention on Narcotic Drugs, the 1971 Convention on Psychotropic Substances and the 1988 United Nations Convention against Illicit Traffic in Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances, “but only when they pose a threat to the peace, order and security of a State or region.” There is thus a strong threshold element that would have to be proved by the prosecution.
-->
